Guide to the Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers UA.30.01.0084
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers
1974-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anderson, Jay Carl
Duke University. University Archives
UA.30.01.0084
15 Linear Feet
Jay Carl Anderson was a Duke University student from 1974 to 1978 and freelance photographer who photographed Duke scenes and athletic events as well as politicians and scenes around Durham and North Carolina. He also served as the editor of the 1978 Chanticleer (Duke University's yearbook). The Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers include images of Anderson's time at Duke, particularly images of East and West campus, athletic events (particularly Duke men's basketball), and Duke students. The collection also includes images of United States Presidents and Presidential Campaigns (particularly Jimmy Carter and the 1976 Democratic National Convention), as well as scenes around Durham, and locations inside and outside of North Carolina.
Arrangement
The Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers are arranged into five series: Duke University, Duke Sports, Durham and North Carolina. Other Topics and Locations, and Exhibitions, Publications, and Writings.
Biographical note
Jay Carl Anderson was a photographer and Duke alumnus who photographed Duke athletic events and campus scenes in the 1970s and 1980s.
Jay Carl Anderson was born in 1956 to Jay C. and Marion C. Anderson. Born in Utica, New York, he grew up in Clinton, New York. His father owned an advertising agency and Jay Anderson learned graphic arts and photography while still in school, first publishing photographs in the Clinton Courier newspaper at age 16. He enrolled at Duke University in 1974 and moved to Durham, North Carolina. He became photography editor for the Chronicle in his freshman year and began working as a freelance photographer, publishing photographs in Parade Magazine and the New York Times while still a student. He covered the 1976 Democratic National Convention in New York as well as other political events and locations in New York and Washington D.C. He traveled to Europe and the Soviet Union for about six months in 1977. In 1976 he joined the staff of the Chanticleer, becoming editor in 1978.
In the summer of 1978, while completing the 1978 Chanticleer, Jay Anderson became involved with modern dance and the American Dance Festival, which came to the Duke campus that same year. He began frequent collaboration with ADF and became the American Dance Festival's official photographer in 1982.
Anderson remained in Durham after graduating from Duke with a BA in History in 1978, and continued to work as a freelance photographer and photojournalist in addition to his work with ADF. He took photographs of Duke athletic events, particularly basketball, throughout the 1980s, and remained involved with the Chanticleer; he also did commercial work in the Triangle and took photographs throughout North Carolina.
Jay Anderson married Saundra Prescott in 1990. The couple moved to St. Petersburg, Florida, in 2010. Jay Carl Anderson died February 8, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2015.
Related Materials
University Archives Photograph Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Chanticleer Photograph Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
University Photography Visual Materials, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
The Chanticleer, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Jay C. Anderson Papers, American Dance Festival Archives. This collection contains Jay Anderson's photographs from his time as the official photographer for the American Dance Festival.
Collection Overview
The Jay Carl Anderson Photographs and Papers include images of Duke University, Durham, Duke athletic events, and many other subjects taken by Jay Anderson throughout the 1970s and 1980s.
The collection includes a large number of photographs taken by Jay Anderson during his time as a student at Duke University in the 1970s, particularly images of the Duke campus, Duke athletic events, and related topics for the 1978 Chanticleer. Also included are images taken in and around Durham after Anderson graduated from Duke, images of politicians and political activity at the national and state level, and locations and events outside of North Carolina. The collection also includes student materials from Anderson's time at Duke and correspondence and publications related to his work as a freelance photographer.
Topics and individuals depicted include Duke's East and West Campus, Duke Blue Devils men's basketball games, student life at Duke in the late 1970s, Duke athletic events, and scenes around Durham and North Carolina. The collection also includes images of politicians such as United States Presidents Jimmy Carter, Gerald Ford, and Ronald Reagan, the 1976 Democratic National Convention, politicians Jesse Jackson, George Wallace, and Walter Mondale, and many other subjects.
The photographs were divided by format and did not include a system to match the same image in different formats. Many negatives were grouped into folders with topical labels, while many others were individually labeled by roll or completely unlabeled. Some negatives were still rolled and uncut, and have been cut to fit into sleeves. Many unlabeled negatives were grouped into labeled folders. Many slides were in labeled containers, while others were sleeved and grouped into folders. Some negatives and slides may contain further identifying information for individual rolls or pages that are not included in folder titles. Most prints were unlabeled, and have been grouped into labeled folders. Some individual prints, likely submitted for publication to clients such as the New York Times, include descriptive captions identifying individuals, events, and/or dates. Not all negatives or slides are represented in prints, and a few prints may not have corresponding negatives or slides.
Photographs taken for the American Dance Festival during Anderson's tenure as official ADF photographer are held at the American Dance Festival Archives.
African Americans -- Durham (N.C.); Political campaigns -- United States.; Political campaigns -- North Carolina; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Conduct of life; Durham (N.C.); North Carolina; Negatives (photographs); Slides (photographs); Prints; Duke University. University Archives; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006; Reagan, Ronald; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998; Duke University -- West Campus; Duke University -- East Campus; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University -- Students; Duke Blue Devils (Basketball team); Duke University -- Football; Democratic National Convention (1976: New York, N.Y.); Duke University -- Athletics; Duke University. Chanticleer staff
- Duke University, 1
  Scope and Contents
  Includes images of buildings, people, events, and activities on West and East Campus as well as images taken for use in the 1978 Chanticleer. Buildings depicted include the Duke Chapel, the Allen Building, the West Campus quad (now Abele Quad), Perkins Library, Pegram dormitory, and many others. Persons depicted include Terry Sanford, members of the Associated Students of Duke University (ASDU), several professors and faculty members, freshmen students during orientation 1975, and many others. Events and activities depicted include several protests, including a rally related to Duke Forest, and many others. A number of images in the Chanticleer subseries are believed to have been taken by other photographers.
  - Campus, 1.1
    Includes images of buildings, people, and events on the Duke University campus. Many of these photographs were taken while Jay Anderson was a student at Duke from 1974-1978, but later images are also included. Locations and topics include the Duke Chapel, the Allen Building, the West Campus quad (now the Julian Abele quad), Pegram dormitory, the statues of James Buchanan Duke and Washington Duke, officers from the Associated Students of Duke University (ASDU), students walking to and from classes, campus buses, campus protests including a protest related to the Duke Forest, classroom interiors, and many other subjects. Several groups of negatives were labeled as East or West Campus, many prints and negatives were unlabeled, although some have additional identifying information. Many of these images may have been taken for the Chanticleer or Chronicle.
    - East Campus, 1975, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - East Campus, 1979, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - East Campus, undated; 120 Roll Film (Box 1)
    - East Campus, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - West Campus, 1975-1976, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - West Campus, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - West Campus, undated; 120 Roll Film (Box 1)
    - West Campus, 1977-1981; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - West Campus (Chapel), undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)
    - Campus, 1974-1975, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - Campus, Other, 1978, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - Campus, 1981 Summer; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - Duke Campus Color, 1977-1987; 3 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - Campus, 1978-1981, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - Campus, 1981, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - Duke Color, 1981-1985; 2 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - Duke Color, 1983-1984; 35mm Color Slides (Box 5)
    - Duke Color, 1983-1984; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Campus, undated; 35mm Color Transparencies and 120 Roll Film Color Transparencies (Box 6)
    - Mixed images of campus and sports, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Campus Photos, 1975; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1976 February 25, 1981 October 6, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1980 June, 1981 June 19, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1981 June 19, 1981 July 27, 1981 September, 1981 November, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1981 June 18, 1981 July 27, 1981 October 6, 1981 November, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1981 June 19, 1981 October 6, 1981 November, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 11)
    - Campus, 1981 October 6, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, 1981 June 18, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, 1981 June, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, 1981 November, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, undated; Color Photographic Prints (Box 12)
    - Campus, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)
  - Other, 1.2
    Includes images of people and events at Duke University. Events and topics include the British American Festival in 1984, images of Duke President Terry Sanford in his office, and other subjects.
    - Other, 1974-1975, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives; 16mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - Other, 1975-1976, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - Other, 1975-1976, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - British American Festival, 1984; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Terry Sanford, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
    - Other, 1975, 1989-1990, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
  - Chanticleer, 1.3
    Includes images taken for the 1978 Chanticleer, most but not all of them photographed by Jay Anderson, as well as images photographed by other individuals for later editions of the Chanticleer. There is some overlap between this subseries and Series 1.1 Campus, Series 1.2 Other, Series 2 Duke Sports, Series 3 Durham and North Carolina, and Series 4.1 Politicians. Many slides in this subseries were labeled with names of staff photographers for the Chanticleer from 1978-1984, and are most likely the work of these photographers. How they came to be included in Jay Anderson's photographs is unknown.
    - 1978 Chanticleer BxW Negatives. 1, 2 folders; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - 1978 Chanticleer BxW Negatives. 2 (1 of 3), 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - 1978 Chanticleer BxW Negatives. 2 (2 of 3), 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 1)
    - 1978 Chanticleer BxW Negatives. 2 (3 of 3), 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Chanticleer Negatives LXX, 1981-1982; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Chronicle, 1975; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Dorm Pictures, 1975, 1976, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 13)
    - 1978 Chanticleer Final Prints, 1977-1978; 3 folders; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 13)
    - 1978 Chanticleer Contact Sheets, undated; 2 folders; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 13)
    - Chanticleer, 1978-1987, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 13)
    - Chanticleer, 1978-1987, undated; 2 folders; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
    - ALBS, circa 1978; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
      Photographs not taken by Jay Anderson
    - Helen Baker, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Dr. John Bell, circa 1978; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Daughtery, 1985; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Marcus Delsasso, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Russel Dionne, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Paul James, circa 1982; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - David Katz, circa 1978; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Mark Kitchens, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Kyung Lee, circa 1979, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Blair Mathies, Jr., circa 1978; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Richard McDonnell, circa 1982; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Tom McLaurin, 1977-1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 6)
    - Tom McLaurin, 1977-1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - McSasso Productions, circa 1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Teresa Miller, circa 1980-1982; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Scott Oates, 1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Scott Picker, circa 1981; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Jay Rathert, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - MS, circa 1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Rick Seidel, circa 1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Shapiro, circa 1978; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Jeff Unger, circa 1983; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Kelly Witter, circa 1983; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - David Woffer, circa 1982; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Various Chanticleer, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
- Duke Sports, 2
  Consists primarily of men’s basketball and football images, with small numbers of images of men’s and women’s soccer, baseball, field hockey, cross-country and track, and tennis. Some basketball and football negatives are dated and include names of the opposing team; many do not. Several prints include descriptive captions giving date, opposing team, and/or player names. Images show players during games as well as coaches, crowds, and other subjects.
  - Basketball, 2.1
    Includes images of games, players, crowds, and other topics related to Duke basketball in the 1970s and 1980s. The majority of images were taken during games, and some negatives and prints indentify individual players, opposing teams, and/or dates, but many do not. Includes images of Cameron Indoor Stadium, Coach Mike Krzyzewski, Coach Bill Foster, and most individual players from 1975-1987.
    - Basketball, 1975, 1976, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1977-1978, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Duke Basketball, 1979-1980; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Duke Basketball, 1979, 1984, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1984; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1985; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1987-1989, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1977-1978, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Duke Basketball, 1979-1980; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Duke Basketball BxW, 1979, 1984, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1984; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1985; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - B-ball, 1987-1989, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Basketball, 1978; 2 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 7)
    - Duke Basketball Color, 1978-1987; 3 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 8)
    - Basketball, 1980, 1985; 35mm Color Slides (Box 8)
    - 84 Duke B-Ball Color, circa 1980s; 2 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 8)
    - 85 Duke B-Ball Color, 1980-1986; 2 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 8)
    - Basketball, 1986-1987, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 8)
    - B-Ball Color Transparency Film, undated; 35mm Color Transparencies (Box 9)
    - Basketball, 1978, 1980, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
    - Basketball, 1980, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
    - Basketball, 1980-1986, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 14)
    - Basketball, undated; 3 folders; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Coach Mike Krzyzewski, Bill Foster, 1970s-1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Johnny Dawkins, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Fans, Cheerleaders, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Basketball Contact Sheets, undated; 2 folders; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Basketball Color, undated; Color Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Photocopies, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Photocopies, 1984, undated (Box 21)
    - Basketball, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)
    - Basketball, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)
  - Football, 2.2
    Includes images of football games, Wallace Wade Stadium, crowds and fans, and other topics related to Duke football. Some images have identifying imformation, but most do not. Some negative rolls also include images from other sports, including soccer.
    - Football, 1974, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Football, 1975, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Football, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 2)
    - Football, 1978-1979, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Football, 1983; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Football, 1984; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Football, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Football, 1980; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - Duke Football - Color, 1982-1985; 3 folders; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - Football, 1980, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 15)
    - Football, 1981-1982, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Football Contact Sheets, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Football, Soccer, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)
  - Other Sports, 2.3
    Includes images of sporting and athletic events at Duke and elsewhere. Includes images of men's and women's soccer, baseball, field hockey, ice hockey, cross-country and track, men's and women's tennis, and other events. Baseball images may include the Durham Bulls or the Bulls Stadium. Most images do not include identifying information.
    - Baseball, 1983; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Baseball, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Cross-Country and Track, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Cross-Country and Track, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Field Hockey, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Ice Hockey, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Rugby, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Soccer, 1983; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Soccer, 1984; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Soccer, 1987, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Soccer, 1984, 1986; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - Soccer, 1980-1981, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Swimming, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Tennis, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Sports, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
- Durham and North Carolina, 3
  Includes images of people, events, and neighborhoods in the city of Durham as well as elsewhere in North Carolina. Many of these images were included in the 1978 Chanticleer. Images include the visit of Archbishop Desmond Tutu to North Carolina Central University in 1986, the demolition of the Washington Duke Hotel in 1975, a parade in downtown Durham, children and adults in neighborhoods near Duke University, the North Carolina State Fair in Raleigh, a factory and farms in and near Little River, North Carolina, and other subjects.
  - Durham, 3.1
    Includes images of people, events, and locations in the city of Durham. Topics include buildings and scenes in downtown Durham, including a parade in 1977 or 1978, the visit of Archbishop Desmond Tutu to North Carolina Central University in 1986, the demolition of the Washington Duke Hotel in 1975, children playing and people outside their homes in neighborhoods around Duke University, and other subjects. Many of these images were likely photographed for the 1978 Chanticleer and several of them are included in that publication.
    - Durham, 1975-1976; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Downtown Durham, 1986, 1987, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Durham, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Dacian Ave.; Univ. Apts., 1979, 1987, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - NCCU: Wilder, Tutu?, 1987; 3 folders; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
      Includes images of Archbishop Desmond Tutu's visit to North Carolina Central University.
    - Durham, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - Durham, 1979-1985; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - Durham, 1975, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Durham, 1975, 1980, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Durham, 1980, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
    - Durham Contact Sheets, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 16)
  - Other North Carolina, 3.2
    Includes images of people, events, and locations around North Carolina. Locations and topics include Chapel Hill, the North Carolina State Fair in Raleigh in 1977, factories and farms near Little River and Orange, mountain scenes, beach scenes, and other subjects.
    - Chapel Hill, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - UNC Football, 1982; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Flying Pigs Band, 1986, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - Little River, Orange Factory, Snow Hill Farm, 1979-1983; 35mm BxW and 120 Roll Film Negatives (Box 3)
    - Little River, Orange Factory, Snow Hill Farm, 1981-1985, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 17)
    - Little River, Orange Factory, Snow Hill Farm, 1985, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 17)
    - Moorhead, 1981-1984; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - NC Beaches, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - NC State Fair, undated; 35mm BxW Negatives (Box 3)
    - State Fair, undated; 35mm Color Slides (Box 9)
    - State Fair, 1980, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 17)
    - State Fair, 1984, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 17)
    - State Fair, undated; BxW Photographic Prints (Box 23)